<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" ><generator uri="https://jekyllrb.com/" version="4.0.0">Jekyll</generator><link href="https://zaidalyafeai.github.io/Blog/feed.xml" rel="self" type="application/atom+xml" /><link href="https://zaidalyafeai.github.io/Blog/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" /><updated>2021-02-18T09:36:10-06:00</updated><id>https://zaidalyafeai.github.io/Blog/feed.xml</id><title type="html">Thoughtspace</title><entry><title type="html">The Road To Self Motivation</title><link href="https://zaidalyafeai.github.io/Blog/2021/02/18/The-Road-to-Self-Motivation.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="The Road To Self Motivation" /><published>2021-02-18T00:00:00-06:00</published><updated>2021-02-18T00:00:00-06:00</updated><id>https://zaidalyafeai.github.io/Blog/2021/02/18/The-Road-to-Self-Motivation</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://zaidalyafeai.github.io/Blog/2021/02/18/The-Road-to-Self-Motivation.html">&lt;h2 id=&quot;the-road-to-self-motivation&quot;&gt;The Road to Self-Motivation&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Humans by instinct usually like freedom and the ability to work on the activities that interest them the most. Unfortunately, for the most part, life responsibilities make it difficult to do such activities because they contradict with other important requirements. That’s why it is important to have the ability to mix interests with responsibilities whenever it is possible. Of course in such circumstances it is difficult because you have to deliver some stuff at your work which you have to finish by some deadline regardless if you like that or not.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I always wondered during my school days why I hated doing homeworks. It was actually a mixture of the lack of motivation and procrastination. Some of them were actually boring so that is another story. Procrastination in the first place kills the motivation because it usually results in a pressure that affects your interest dramatically. Suppose for example you have a project that you really like and would like to read more about and do many interesting stuff to investigate. However, you just delayed everything till it is too late. When deadlines arrive it is difficult to have the motivation and interest you had initially because you just care about finishing it asap. This is a big problem because your motivation just wears out and the common goal becomes to just finish. Working with things earlier preserves motivation and gives you the energy to pursue your interest. I remember in my bachelor degree that I liked some courses and I just regret not reading more because I got caught on homeworks and exams and didn’t have the time to enrich my knowledge more. This is a common problem because students usually look at the end result of getting a good grade and don’t have the motivation to understand the subject more. That’s why it is important to mix the things you have to do with the interests that you like. For instance, suppose that you like a certain sport and you have to choose a topic for your term paper. Why not mix these things together instead of working on a very boring topic that your instructor just chose for you. The importance of such decisions really escalates when you have some important projects that you have to work on for a long period of time, like a thesis for example. Long term projects are really tricky to work with because if you lack the motivation you will just quit. That’s why it’s important to choose wisely especially if you have some ‘say’ on what to work on. This can also be generalized at work even though the decisions might be completely to your boss. Sometimes you will have the chance to suggest an interesting project for your company that really aligns with your interests. Of course, that might get rejected but at least that tells your employer about your interests and how much they could help in the workplace.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The perfect scenario of working on the things you like might not exist in real life, but the reason might not because it is not there, rather that you didn’t really try to find it. It is ok to explore many options till you find something you really like and intersects with your daily deliverables. Not to mention that you can work on other side projects ‘maybe smaller’ to keep yourself motivated and maybe apply your knowledge in that field at your workplace or school.&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name></name></author><summary type="html">The Road to Self-Motivation</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Procrastination But Mitigated</title><link href="https://zaidalyafeai.github.io/Blog/2020/12/13/Procrastination-But-Mitigated.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Procrastination But Mitigated" /><published>2020-12-13T00:00:00-06:00</published><updated>2020-12-13T00:00:00-06:00</updated><id>https://zaidalyafeai.github.io/Blog/2020/12/13/Procrastination-But-Mitigated</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://zaidalyafeai.github.io/Blog/2020/12/13/Procrastination-But-Mitigated.html">&lt;p&gt;Procrastination But Mitigated&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;With many commitments in life, many deadlines come to existence. The priority of each one might be different but at some point it is important to be able to fulfil most of these tasks. From an academic point of view, each week we might have a single or multiple deliverables and this seems to increase as you climb the ranking ladder. I remember when I was a bachelor and mostly focused on homeworks, exams and projects. Now, as a PhD student many commitments are there and it is difficult to keep track and organize your time in an effective way. It is difficult to lay down a plan that works for every one but at least you can get some beneficial hints.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;One thing that I really was good at is the ability of dealing with many deliverables in an effective way. We will assume that we have multiple tasks that need to be fulfilled in a given time. There are many steps in such a case. The first one is to order your deliverables in terms of priority. Given the queue of ordered jobs, you need to allocate a time for each job that is proportional to the complexity/priority of the task. Then you split the job in multiple days until the deadline. Let us take an example. Suppose that you have 3 tasks each one has 6, 4, 2 priority and we have to finish them in a week. Then, we will give the tasks 10, 8, 6 hours respectively. After that, we will divide the time by the remaining days. Hence we will allocate for each task 10/7, 8/7, 6/7 hours daily. I believe this method is really effective because of many reasons. The first one is the ability of working on multiple tasks in parallel. This allows moving flexibly from one task to another. The second is the ability of reversing the effect of procrastination by allowing flexible remaining time that can change if the task needs more time than originally allocated. Finally, working on multiple tasks gives the impression of satisfaction of finishing fragments of each task in each day. Compare that to finishing each task one day before the deadline and having to deal with the stress of not being able to deliver on time. This approach can be implemented if each task has a different deadline. In such a case we have to scale each task by dividing by the remaining time of each task.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Giving a reasonable time for each task only comes with experience. I’ve suffered from the problem of underestimating a task and only giving it a low priority and then discovering that it needs more time. However, with implementing this approach many times I’ve gained some confidence about how much time each task needs and so forth. Also, there might be other aspects that might affect the priority of a task like it’s importance. For example, if you have some important project that you need to submit then you might give it more time for the sake of making sure everything is fine. Moreover, try to overestimate the required time for finishing a task. This helps in reducing the penalty of poorly chosen time slots.&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name></name></author><summary type="html">Procrastination But Mitigated</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">The Ups And Downs Of A Graduate Student</title><link href="https://zaidalyafeai.github.io/Blog/2020/11/28/The-Ups-and-Downs-of-A-Graduate-Student.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="The Ups And Downs Of A Graduate Student" /><published>2020-11-28T00:00:00-06:00</published><updated>2020-11-28T00:00:00-06:00</updated><id>https://zaidalyafeai.github.io/Blog/2020/11/28/The-Ups-and-Downs-of-A-Graduate-Student</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://zaidalyafeai.github.io/Blog/2020/11/28/The-Ups-and-Downs-of-A-Graduate-Student.html">&lt;p&gt;The Ups and Downs of a Graduate Student&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I have been dreaming about doing research since I started as a bachelor student in computer science. The idea of doing original research was really mysterious and exciting at the same time. I didn’t do any research at that period of my life (something that I would consistently regret), so the idea was still vague to me. I did some quick research but it was only in mathematics and published a 200 page on advanced integration. That strengthened my background in mathematics but I would struggle to apply that in my field. Given that, I was still looking forward to doing more research and this time in computer science.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As excited, I started my masters in computer science and I would still wonder around the different topics to see the topics that interest me the most. Still, I would move from one topic to another lost between the things that interest me and those that seem popular in the literature. At that time, deep learning was capturing a lot of hype but I lacked all the necessary requirements (no background whatsoever). I spent a whole semester reading about different papers in the field. I was under the pressure of starting my thesis topic in computer vision but was stressed about the idea of skipping some necessary concepts. I would say, that period was the most self-doubting period in my life as a student. A lot of expectation with little to advance. You know when you expect doing something novel in the field and end up doing way below the state of the art. Maybe the problem was going in a direction where a lot of researchers had spent a lot of time and experience in and I am just starting and expecting to break the numbers. I came to know that this is usual as a starting graduate student but the idea of getting sota results was still intriguing to me. Maybe I was supposed to think about something fundamental rather than challenging numbers.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;After three years of struggling I finished my masters degree with a lot of lessons that I learnt. I started my PhD with much more confidence and a little more narrowed research. I completely switched from doing computer vision to NLP. This improved my confidence a lot. Moreover, collaborating with others has benefited me a lot instead of just battling thoughts in my mind. Discussing ideas with colleagues was really beneficial to me to improve my research experience. Still, I would question myself and whether I am making the correct decisions. The idea of creating something novel still confuses me and whether I can do it or not. Working on different things has benefited me a lot and gave me the motive to succeed in many different endeavours. I am currently in my second year and hoping to learn more and do original research related to Arabic NLP.&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name></name></author><summary type="html">The Ups and Downs of a Graduate Student</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Three Dimensional Learning In Cs</title><link href="https://zaidalyafeai.github.io/Blog/2020/07/18/Three-Dimensional-Learning-in-CS.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title=" Three Dimensional Learning In Cs" /><published>2020-07-18T00:00:00-05:00</published><updated>2020-07-18T00:00:00-05:00</updated><id>https://zaidalyafeai.github.io/Blog/2020/07/18/-Three-Dimensional-Learning-in-CS</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://zaidalyafeai.github.io/Blog/2020/07/18/Three-Dimensional-Learning-in-CS.html">&lt;p&gt;Three-Dimensional Learning in Computer Science&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I remember when I was a kid how much I was impressed by how computers work. The idea of writing simple code to make complicated operations and interfaces was puzzling for me. The first program I made was a calculator using Visual Basic. I remember how back then it was easy to find materials to learn about programming. It is safe to say that Computer science has the largest materials for learning on the web compared to any other field of study. There are three important dimensions which helped to expand the field in the way we are seeing it today.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The first one is problem-solving. Compared to other other subjects like engineering for instance, you can practice solving a lot of examples and more than 90% of students will solve the same problems using the same approach. However in computer science things are different. The art of problem solving keeps the mind active and people challenge each other to find brilliant solutions. You might spend days trying to solve a simple programming question making it more efficient for instance. On other hand it makes us more resistant to failure. You know things will work at the end but you might spend hours trying to solve a bug. Computer science combines thinking about problems as well as writing beautiful code.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The second dimension is writing open source code. This is related to the first dimension because we are solving problems by writing a code. Look at answers to questions in stack overflow to see the variety of solutions to a given problem. Some solutions are simple and neat others are complicated yet more efficient. There is some beauty and enjoyment in writing code. It is difficult to succeed in this field if you don’t like to spend hours writing code only. For me, it is like magic to write a few lines of code and you get a widely used tool that can be easily distributed. Moreover, writing open source code helps expand the knowledge because we can reuse it to make it more complicated and at the same time more high level. One of the best websites that helped the distribution of the code is GitHub where code is easily accessible and can be forked to improve.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The last dimension is distributed knowledge using books, articles and videos. Computer science is one of the few subjects that has millions of articles online on different languages. As of July-2020, stackoverflow which is one of the largest question answering websites for developers is ranked 45 in global internet engagement according to Alexa. This tells alot about how much engagement is related to programming and computer science. By nature, we like to write tutorials, make videos and also share this knowledge. This distribution of knowledge has allowed the field to advance dramatically in the era of the internet. Not to mention the number of publications each year that helps advance the field in different fields. Moreover, the current advances in machine learning have helped the field gain more popularity as many students from different studies are interested in incorporating these algorithms in their field of study.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In short, there are three reasons that made computer science shape the way we see it this day. These are problems solving, writing open source code and distribution of knowledge. Computer science is closely related to other fields like software and computer engineering and it is difficult to neglect the impact they had on the development of the field.&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name></name></author><summary type="html">Three-Dimensional Learning in Computer Science</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Mutlitasking As A Graduate Student</title><link href="https://zaidalyafeai.github.io/Blog/2020/07/17/Mutlitasking-as-a-graduate-student.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Mutlitasking As A Graduate Student" /><published>2020-07-17T00:00:00-05:00</published><updated>2020-07-17T00:00:00-05:00</updated><id>https://zaidalyafeai.github.io/Blog/2020/07/17/Mutlitasking-as-a-graduate-student</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://zaidalyafeai.github.io/Blog/2020/07/17/Mutlitasking-as-a-graduate-student.html">&lt;p&gt;Multitasking as a Graduate Student&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;By nature we can process different things at the same time. We can do multiple tasks on the same day. Usually we can prioritize different tasks according to our schedule. Our procedure to handle different tasks might be different and this is usually affected by our experience and the nature of the tasks.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As a PhD student I usually work on different projects. It is becoming essential for me to organize my time such that I don’t cramp myself with different duties. Usually, If I only have one task I start doing it early. For instance, if I have a submission after one week, regardless if it needs a lot of work or not, I start early. This allows me to improve my work and look at it from different angles. The quality increases dramatically when I start early as opposed to doing everything in just one day. Early scheduling increases your working hours but it gives the chance to work less in a day as well as resolve issues that might emerge. Furthermore, procrastinating things till the last moment might be catastrophic especially if you discover that the allocated time was not enough.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Usually, when working on different tasks you have to organize your time carefully. For instance, I might have a paper submission, presentation, coding and writing articles. I start first by prioritizing the things that are very important. But prioritizing doesn’t mean doing them first but allocating more span of time. For instance, paper submission will take a lot of time so I might take one week with two hours a day to work on it. On the other hand, writing an article might take two hours to finish. It is important to recognize these things earlier and allocate the time and effort. This allows me to work on different things on the same day. For instance, two hours writing a paper, three hours coding and half-hour to work on the presentation. The next day I might remove the less important thing which might be the presentation and work on the article.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Working on different things is important because it gives your mind some space for resting. The different tasks I mentioned have different properties. Writing a paper for instance requires a lot of mental power. While the presentation is easier, I might watch an entertaining video at the same time. It is essential not to work on many things that require a lot of mental concentration on the same day. Moreover, working on different tasks gives the impression of success because finishing one task will make you happier. A failure or closed door on one task motivates you to work on another task.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;While working on different tasks is important it has its downsides. You have to be careful not to overkill yourself with lots of long tasks in parallel. For instance, working on three projects where each one takes more than a month might be a bad idea. Indeed, it depends on the capacity of the person because some people have the strength to do it. Others are forced because they are ordered to work on these tasks. If you have the chance, limit yourself by knowing your capabilities. Moreover, don’t work on multiple projects that consume a lot of mental and physical power. Try to keep balance between these things because it will wear you out.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Some people have different strategies when working on different tasks. One might prefer finishing one task at a time. But, from experience it is important that you know how much time each task will need. If the allocated time is less, it will have bad ramifications. That’s why I don’t prefer this approach. It might be interesting to consider a hybrid approach where you finish some tasks that are more important and work on less important tasks in parallel. Indeed, with experience you know your capacity and it is up to you to decide the best approach.&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name></name></author><summary type="html">Multitasking as a Graduate Student</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Optimization In Real Life</title><link href="https://zaidalyafeai.github.io/Blog/2020/07/15/Optimization-in-Real-Life.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Optimization In Real Life" /><published>2020-07-15T00:00:00-05:00</published><updated>2020-07-15T00:00:00-05:00</updated><id>https://zaidalyafeai.github.io/Blog/2020/07/15/Optimization-in-Real-Life</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://zaidalyafeai.github.io/Blog/2020/07/15/Optimization-in-Real-Life.html">&lt;p&gt;Optimization in Real Life&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As a researcher in computer science I try to create a resemblance between the concepts I study in machine learning and real life. Machine learning has a lot of maths but let us just ignore that and focus on high level concepts. Generally speaking, in machine learning the pipeline consists of a model, an objective function and an algorithm that attempts to maximize/minimize the objective function. The algorithm makes changes to the parameters of the model in order to achieve near-optimal results. But, how is that related to real life ?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In real life, we are in some way or another choosing our actions in order to optimize an objective function. As we learn to walk, we try to reduce the possibility of colliding our legs together and fall miserably. In simple terms, we are trying to minimize the objective function which calculates risk of falling. As we enter the war of the stock market we are trying to maximize the objective of earning money. The design of an objective function in real life is usually easy. However, the algorithm we take to do that might be long and rewarding or sometimes short and unethical. You might spend many years trying to learn about how the stock market works. You attempt to ask experts, learn more about stock models and possibly take some courses. However, as humans we are usually lazy. We try to do shortcuts which might allow us to ascend faster in our competition towards fame and popularity - maximize our objective function - but on the other hand we might go to jail if we don’t follow the law. In real life there are regularizers: upper/lower estimators that limit our algorithm to maximize and minimize the objective function. Health is a regularizer, you might get sick and stop earning money for a period of time. There are many other regularizers like time, family, law, etc. In our journey, we try to reduce these regularizers but they are there and we have to deal with them.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Theoretically speaking, we can design different algorithms to optimize objective functions. You can earn money by working as a doctor, engineer or like me in academia. Each one of us made that choice and we are trying to maximize our earning through our choice of design. Early on your career you might have chosen to go through college, graduate and then get a job. In your second year you decided that your design was incorrect, you dropped out college. We make these choices all the time; we might get lucky and succeed and more frequently we might fail and retry. As humans we are stubborn and try to navigate different routes into optimizations.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Sometimes, the design of an objective function is not in our hand. In a world where millions of people use social media, we don’t have much choice. These objective functions have been designed carefully by social media creators to encourage people to look for efficient algorithms for optimization. Our objective mostly is predetermined through a lot of flashy words: likes, retweets, views, favorites, followers, connections, etc. The creators of social media were very smart in designing these objectives. As you create your first account, you try to optimize these numbers because everyone does. Take twitter for instance, lots of likes, means lots of followers, verified, popular, sponsorships, ads and then wala you hit the jackpot. Content creators are forced to ask for likes, subscriptions, views, clickbaits in order to make money.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Our definition of right and wrong is changing according to different metrics in social media. Have you ever changed your way of tweeting because you didn’t get much likes? If a certain tweet will get you 1000 likes will you do it? regardless of the ramifications. Say, you are a creator on youtube and you made a video that got you only a couple of views. Then you made a completely different video that got you thousands of views. While the reason might be completely random you are determined to continue in the line of the second video. You want to make money and you want to make it fast. Our way of thinking is affected a lot by these metrics and our sole purpose is becoming to optimize them. As we try to optimize these metrics our virtues change because they might contradict with our objective function.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Most of the time we do follow the herd and do the same thing. We optimize the same objective function whether designed by us or other entities. We don’t question our actions and we just do them unconsciously. There is no quick way of getting popular, receiving praise or making money. Most of the numbers we look to optimize don’t make any sense and they are just consuming our soul. They make us lie, change our attitude, think uncritically and make unethical decisions.&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name></name></author><summary type="html">Optimization in Real Life</summary></entry></feed>